<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: maven | Wordsi by Fozzie The Beat]]></title>
  <link href="http://fozziethebeat.github.com/blog/categories/maven/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fozziethebeat.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-12T23:07:16-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://fozziethebeat.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Keith Stevens]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[fozziethebeat@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sonatype and Scala: A relationship of trickery]]></title>
    <link href="http://fozziethebeat.github.com/blog/2012/06/02/sonatype-and-scala-a-relationship-of-trickery/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-02T22:28:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://fozziethebeat.github.com/blog/2012/06/02/sonatype-and-scala-a-relationship-of-trickery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Open source projects are amazing.  They let you easily share the work you do
with others so that they can iterate and improve upon your ideas, an especially
invaluable quality when you later move on to other things.  <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a> in a very
similar fashion makes sharing open source (or even closed source) java projects
super easy.  If you structure your codebase in a <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a> way and register an
account with <a href="https://oss.sonatype.org/">Sonatype</a>, you can get your project's jars distributed
worldwide so that anyone and everyone can used your stuff without having to
download and compile your code.</p>

<p>For pure java projects, this process is utterly <a href="https://docs.sonatype.org/display/Repository/Sonatype+OSS+Maven+Repository+Usage+Guide">trivial</a>, just follow some
instructions and it all works out beautifully.  But java is verbose and often
prefer to use <a href="http://www.scala-lang.org/">Scala</a>, especially for small prototype systems.  But how do
you deploy a mavenized scala project with <a href="https://oss.sonatype.org/">Sonatype</a>?  Well, it all pretty
much works out except that you need to create a jar of <strong>javadocs</strong> before
<a href="https://docs.sonatype.org/display/Repository/Sonatype+OSS+Maven+Repository+Usage+Guide#SonatypeOSSMavenRepositoryUsageGuide-6.CentralSyncRequirement">Sonatype</a> will let you publish anything.  Not being java and all, scala does
not do this out of the box, and maven won't either.  But, there's a cute hack
you can do if you're using maven 3.0.  Just add this snippet to your pom file
and watch the deployment rock:</p>

<p>``` xml
  <build></p>

<pre><code>&lt;plugins&gt;
  ...
  &lt;plugin&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;net.alchim31.maven&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;scala-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;3.0.2&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;executions&gt;
      &lt;execution&gt;
        &lt;id&gt;javadoc-jar&lt;/id&gt;
        &lt;phase&gt;package&lt;/phase&gt;
        &lt;goals&gt;
          &lt;goal&gt;doc-jar&lt;/goal&gt;
        &lt;/goals&gt;
      &lt;/execution&gt;
    &lt;/executions&gt;
  &lt;/plugin&gt;
&lt;/plugins&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  </build>
```</p>

<p>This uses the versitile <a href="http://davidb.github.com/scala-maven-plugin/">scala maven plugin</a> and runs the <code>doc-jar</code> goal to
build scala docs every time you type <code>mvn package</code> or some command that depends
on <code>mvn package</code>, this includes <code>mvn deploy</code>.  The id bit creates a
<code>javadoc.jar</code> containing the scaladoc.  So with just that tidbit, you can deploy
your maven projects to <a href="https://oss.sonatype.org/">Sonatype</a> with no issues at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
