<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: dilemmas | Wordsi by Fozzie The Beat]]></title>
  <link href="http://fozziethebeat.github.com/blog/categories/dilemmas/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fozziethebeat.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-02T14:21:02+09:00</updated>
  <id>http://fozziethebeat.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Keith Stevens]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[fozziethebeat@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moral Dilemmas]]></title>
    <link href="http://fozziethebeat.github.com/blog/2012/03/04/moral-dilemmas/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-04T19:03:00+09:00</updated>
    <id>http://fozziethebeat.github.com/blog/2012/03/04/moral-dilemmas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is the nature of a moral dilemma?  How moral can any dilemma be?  Are some
dilemmas inherently moral free or can any problem be cast into some level of a
moral quandary? And if that's true, how do you get to this quandary state and
where do you go from there?</p>

<p>These questions have been bubbling around in my mind for the past couple months,
ever since I read a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/13/opinion/if-it-feels-right.html">New York Times Op-Ed post</a> about moral dilemmas and a new
book called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lost-Transition-Dark-Emerging-Adulthood/dp/0199828024">"Lost in Transition"</a>.  In the NYTimes post, the David Brooks notes
that the authors of "Lost in Transition" found that modern high school students
are unequipped to think about things in moral terms.  For instance, The authors
posed some questions to students and said the following:</p>

<p>{% blockquote %}
Not many of them have previously given much or any thought to many of the kinds of questions about morality that we asked.
{% endblockquote %}</p>

<p>I haven't read the book in detail, so I can't really comment on their full
findings, proposals, or methodology, so I'm not about to comment on that now.
Instead, I got to asking myself the many questions up above.  In particular, I
wanted to know how I could pose daily activities as moral dilemmas.  I don't
often put things into directly moral terms, but I was a Teaching Assistant for
a class focused on Ethics in Engineering, so I <em>should</em> be equipped to do some
pretty solid moral analysis if I apply myself.</p>

<p>So, I'd like to try and break down some seemingly non-moral problems in totally
moral terms.  And to start, let's go with <em>Doing the dishes</em>.</p>

<p>Now, normally, you might look at the task of dishes and think that it's just
something you have to do.  Often it's a little boring, or even a little
unpleasant based on your cooking forays, but it's not too often that people feel
morally <em>conflicted</em> about when and whether or not they do their dishes.  But if
you live with other people and share a common cooking space, I would argue that
it is inherently a moral issue.  Namely, it's an issue about acting with empathy.</p>

<p>According to Wikipedia, the world's coolest encyclopedia, <em>empathy</em> is defined
as</p>

<p>{% blockquote %}</p>

<pre><code>the capacity to recognize and, to some extent, share feelings (such as
sadness or happiness) that are being experienced by another sentient or
semi-sentient being
</code></pre>

<p>{% endblockquote %}</p>

<p>So how does empathy relate <em>at all</em> to doing the dishes? Well, by living in an
apartment shared with other people, your actions implicitly affect the
livelihood and wellbeing of others.  So let's break down the task of dishes into
two aspects: your choice of actions and the possible affects it can have on
others.   When it comes to doing dishes, there's really two choices you can
make:</p>

<ol>
<li>do the dishes</li>
<li>don't do the dishes</li>
</ol>


<p>And everyone in the house will likely have one of two reactions to dirty dishes:</p>

<ol>
<li>dirty dishes are not a problem</li>
<li>dirty dishes are frustrating</li>
</ol>


<p>With regards to clean dishes, it's fairly safe to assume that everyone enjoys
and appreciates clean dishes, i've certainly not met anyone bothered by a clean
plate or glass.  So how do these reactions connect to whether or not you
should make those dishes sparkly clean?  Well, by leaving dirty dishes you're
doing one of two things:</p>

<ol>
<li>you're assuming that everyone is ok with dirty dishes</li>
<li>you don't about how others feel about dirty dishes</li>
</ol>


<p>I would argue that both cases are a failure in empathy.  By assuming that others
share your same reaction to doing the dishes, you're failing to recognize that
others in the house may feel otherwise (first half of our empathy definition).
If for instance, a roommate has a horrible case of OCD and emotionally breakdown
upon the sight of food encrusted dishes, failing to do the dishes may make this
particular person deeply wounded.  And by simply ignoring how other's feel about
dishes (the second, sharing, half of empathy), even if you recognize that they
may feel differently, you're actively choosing not to share those feelings.</p>

<p>What happens if you <em>do</em> clean the dishes and leave things sparkly, fresh, and
lemon scented?  You're still making an assumption about how other's feel about
dishes, but you're making the most conservative assumption you can; most people
prefer clean dishes so by cleaning you're <em>less</em> likely to cause any emotional
breakdowns, or in more normal cases, mild frustration.  Assuming that you like
to be happy, doing the dishes is the only <em>empathy</em> filled action available, it
makes the fewest and most conservative assumptions about what makes others happy.</p>

<p>So that's one way to break down the task of dishes into a moral dilemma.  So the
next time you make a mess in the kitchen and ask yourself "should I clean
those?"  You can make a handy debate about it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
